Emrakul, The World Anew
is probably one of the
most powerful
Eldrazi cards
printed to
date, but
the wording on the
card can be a bit
confusing.  So in
today's video,
I'll go into detail about
what exactly Emrakul does,
what exactly it's
protected against, a cool
turn three combo you'll likely
see in
the future, and how you
can counter this
card if you
find yourself under attack.
They drove.  So Emrakul
is a
12-mana Eldrazi legendary with
12/12 stats
that says, "When you
cast this
spell,
gain control
of all creatures
under
target player's control."
It has flying and
protection against spells
and permanents that
were played this
turn.  "And when Emrakul, The
World Anew leaves the
battlefield, sacrifice
all creatures you
control."  And finally
, she has madness.
Pay six
colorless mana.  So
let's start at the very
top of this
text box.  When
you cast this
spell,
gain control
of all creatures
under
target player's control.  As
with previous
Eldrazi Titans, this
ability triggers
when cast.  So
, when Emrakul hits the
stack, this ability
activates,
meaning that even
if Emrakul is cancelled, you
still gain
control of all of the
target
player's creatures.  And since
Emrakul never
leaves the battlefield,
you don't have to
sacrifice all of your
creatures, including the ones
you just
gained control of.  And one
last note:
this ability always
triggers before
Emrakul enters the field.  Well, this
part is pretty self-
explanatory
.  And protection from
spells and
permanents that were
played this turn.
As a reminder: protection
means that a player
or permanent with
protection from X
cannot be damaged,
enchanted,
equipped, or
strengthened by a permanent
with property X,
cannot be blocked by
creatures with
property X, and
cannot be targeted by
spells or
abilities of sources with
property X. If
you want to learn
more about protection,
watch this video.
In this case,
the spell, according to
rules 112.1, is a
card on the
stack.  So Emrakul has
protection against all types of
spells, including
instant spells,
sorceries, and
enchantments.  So, Path
to Exile, Dreadbore, or Pacifism will
not be able to
target Emrakul.  Don't
forget that creatures are
also spells
while they are on the stack.  So
Emrakul has protection from
them as well.  Therefore,
creatures with a
cast ability, such as
Ulamog, the Ceaseless Hunger, will
also not be able to target
Emrakul.
Next part:
defense against
permanents that were
played this turn.
This part is a little
easier to understand.  All
you need to
do is
check: was
this permanent
played this
turn?  If the answer is
yes, Emrakul has
protection against this.
If the answer is "no,"
then she has no
protection against this.  So, a
good example here
would be Solitude or Leyline
Binding.  Both of these cards
have trigger
abilities that can
exile creatures when
they enter the
battlefield.  So, a played
Leyline Binding or Solitude will
never be able to
banish Emrakul,
as they were
played this turn.
It is important to note:
for Emrakul to have
protection from
the spell, it must
be cast.
So, if Emrakul
was on the battlefield and
you already had Solitude in play
, you could simply
cast Ephemerate on
Solitude.  When Solitude
enters the
battlefield, it becomes a
new game
object.  And since
she wasn't cast, you'll
be able to channel
her ability onto Emrakul
.  The same
could be said if
you introduced Leyline Binding into the
game with
something like Show and
Tell.  Leyline doesn't
play out, so you
can banish
Emrakul.  Let's talk
about the last
ability—Madness.
Madness is a
mechanic from the
2002 release of Torment that says:
if you discard this
card, discard it into
exile.  When you
do, play it
for its Madness cost or
put it into the graveyard.
At first glance, this
looks like a way to
get Emrakul at a
discount.  But one of the
most
underrated
features of Madness is that
it breaks
time constraints.
If you want
to learn more about
how to break
time limits,
watch this video.
In short,
since Madness
allows us to play a
card for its cost,
we can play
Emrakul at instant
speed.  Here is a
situation we are
likely to see in
the near future.  Our
opponent has three
"Tron" lands in play,
allowing him
to generate seven
colorless mana.  And
they also have The
Underworld Cookbook in the game.  Since
we are playing a
mono-red deck
and are not afraid of anything,
we attack our opponent.
But before dealing
damage, they simply
activate their
cookbook,
dropping Emrakul.    The
Madness ability is triggered.  They then
return their
"Throne" lands to
gain six mana,
pay it, and
cast Emrakul.
Emrakul's ability
triggers when drawn, and they
gain control
of all our
attackers,
preventing
any damage.  Now
they have all of our creatures
and a 12/12 creature that will
likely
win the game
next turn.  So
how do you deal with Emrakul
?  There are several ways.
First, you can
use
cards like Whirlwind
Denial and Summary Dismissal to
cancel both
Emrakul itself and its
trigger ability.
Don't forget that
Emrakul's "
spell protection
" ability only takes effect
once she's already on the
battlefield.  Second,
if they're already on the
battlefield, you can
use
table-clearing cards
that don't require a target
and don't deal damage,
like Day of Judgment or
Black Sun's Zenith.  And finally
, you can
hope that you have a
permanent on the table that
can deal with
Emrakul the turn before
it comes into
play.  For example, something
like "Avatar of Woe"
or "Vraska, Relic Seeker."  But
honestly, the
best way
to counter Emrakul
is to use
banishment effects
like Ephemerate or
Scrollshift on
cards like Solitude and
Leyline Binding.  So what do you
think of the new
Emrakul?  Do you think
it will break the
Modern format?  As always, like
if
you learned something new.
Watch these videos
if you want to
learn more about
protecting or violating
time limits.  And
subscribe, or
I promise to
unleash the Eldrazi
on Bloomborough.  Thanks for
watching, see you
in the next video.